A Guide to the Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge Correspondence 1810-1861
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 October 23 (Box 1)
  writes of her expectation of more visitors due to the meeting of the Presbyterian Synod at Charlottesville, on October 27, the decline of Maria Carr, the visit of Captain [Claudius] Crozet and Mr. Fairfax with Nicholas [Trist?] following their survey of the Kanawha [River?], John Patton Emmet's interest in Mary Byrd Tucker, a visit to the Library at the University where the rules forbid anyone to carry a volume past the precincts of the institution, and Francis Gilmer's poor health
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 October 31 (Box 1)
  writes concerning General John Hartwell Cocke and his wife at Bremo in Fluvanna County, her impatience with Presbyterian preachers, the birth of a girl to the Dunglison's, and a riding accident involving two University students
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 November 10 (Box 1)
  sends the news that Ellen's trunks were lost at sea on the brig Washington which included all of the letters from her grandfather and mother, and refers to a letter to the editor of Central Gazette from [J.H.I.] Browere jesting about the episode with Jefferson's life mask and misrepresenting what actually occurred
- J[oseph] C[oolidge], Jr. to Randolph 1825 November 11 (Box 1)
  refers to Ellen's lost trunks, a recent fire suffered by the Coolidge family, and Ellen's adjustment to life in Boston
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 November 16 (Box 1)
  talks about her distress over the loss of Ellen's trunks, mentions some of the things remaining at Monticello that they might send to her, including her grandfather's plan to send her the writing desk upon which the Declaration of Independence was written, her suspicion of Ellen's pregnancy, news of Virginia Trist's pregnancy, and Thomas Jefferson's disappointment in the color of the pillar for his bust
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1825 November 20 (Box 1)
  reflects upon her lost treasures in the brig Washington and her concern over her family's misfortunes
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 November 24 (Box 1)
  shares her frustration at having no time to read or to draw, saying "I know I wish I could do something to support myself instead of this unprofitable drudgery of keeping house here, but I suppose not until we sink entirely will it do for the granddaughters of Thomas Jefferson to take in work or keep a school, and we shall hold out for some time yet; ours is not a gallopping consumption but one of those lingering diseases which drags on for years and years," and mentions the resumption of Jefferson's horseback rides
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1825 November 26 (Box 1)
  lists the contents of a new shipment of articles to Ellen the chief of which is the desk associated with the Declaration of Independence, and including Jefferson's sugar dish used in Paris, sends some recipes except those unnecessary for a "town lady" and mentions Wilson Cary's agreement to work in the Fluvanna County Clerk's office
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1825] November 27 (Box 1)
  writes of details concerning the destruction of her belongings at sea and her devotion to her family
- Virginia Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1825 December 4 (Box 1)
  tells how she misses Ellen's lively conversation in the drawing room, mentions the lack of opportunity for self improvement, her preoccupation with the sewing needle, Sally [Cole's] visit to Monticello with Mrs. Key, Sally's contentment nursing the Key baby, and her inquiry about Ellen
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1826 January 2 (Box 2)
  voices her discouragement concerning the ignorance of Americans on the subject of the North American Indian, especially in the book by [John Dunn?] Hunter which General George Rogers Clark pronounced in error concerning the region of the Osages; and remarks upon the respect shown to New England clergymen by her neighbors
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1826 January 23 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the public sale of Edgehill, her high opinion of her brother Jefferson, her use of the Declaration of Independence desk, the safe arrival of items shipped from Monticello, and refers to a letter from Mrs. [Gouverneur Morris] abusing De Witt Clinton and other individuals who bother her husband from time to time for favors
- Joseph and Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1826 February 8 (Box 2)
  express concern that Cornelia may not get to visit them due to financial problems with the tobacco sales, items sent to Thomas Jefferson and family include a piano and French brandy
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 February 23 (Box 2)
  describes Thomas Jefferson's lottery scheme to sell the mill and some land to pay his debts and the difficulty in getting the bill through the General Assembly due to the precedent it might set, and refers to the death of Anne Cary Bankhead and the illness of her baby
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1826 February 27 (Box 2)
  writes of her regret at not being present to comfort her mother over the death of her sister, mentions the passage of the lottery bill for Thomas Jefferson by the Virginia Legislature, the sympathy of New England for his plight and their proposal of voting a sum to "an old revolutionary patriot and the friend of science and the arts," and discusses the progress of female education in Massachusetts
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge 1826 March 1 (Box 2)
  relates the problems of getting Cornelia to Boston for a visit, the success of Thomas Jefferson's lottery proposal, Jefferson Randolph's future trip to New York on that business, the plan for Ellen Bankhead and the newborn infant to live with Martha, and the reconciliation of the family with Charles Lewis Bankhead
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 March 18 (Box 2)
  plans to accompany Jefferson Randolph to Boston as soon as his business is completed at Bedford, says that the family is awaiting the arrival of Virginia's piano by boat, describes meeting Mrs. Bonnycastle, Virginia's health, Dr. Emmet's poor health and his brother who was involved in several escapades at the University
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1826 March 23 (Box 2)
  shares her opinion of Mrs. Ritchie and her ideas on child rearing, her opinion of society in Boston, and a description of the Coolidge household
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 April 5 (Box 1)
  discusses Thomas Jefferson's financial condition after the passage of the lottery bill, which would pay his debts and leave him Monticello for his lifetime, her worries over their future, the five thousand dollars a year in interest alone her father had to pay, describes the circumstances of the sale of Edgehill, the impatience of Thomas Mann Randolph's creditors, Jefferson Randolph's role in the sale, the injunction brought by T.M. Randolph against his son Jefferson, the slanderous and untrue rumors concerning Jefferson taking advantage of his father over the sale of Edgehill, since he was the highest bidder, stoutly defends Jefferson's motives and actions concerning the whole affair, describes the shock to Thomas Jefferson when he realized that Monticello would have to be sold and how Jefferson conceived the idea of the lottery to satisfy his debts, and Harriet [Randolph's?] plan to open a school for girls
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge 1826 April 8 (Box 2)
  thanks Joseph for news of Ellen's successful childbirth, shares their enjoyment of the piano, her father's intention of buying one if the lottery turns out well, and the reduction of his dose of laudanum to seventy drops without ill effect
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 April 16 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the health of Anne Cary Bankhead's children, her grandfather's resumption of the practice of inviting students to Sunday dinner to the annoyance of the family, the refusal of the law professorship by William Wirt, and Sally [Cole's] concern and inquiries concerning Ellen
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1826 May 9 (Box 2)
  describes her daughter Ellen Randolph Coolidge's baptism, her nervousness at the affair, her enjoyment of having Cornelia visit, and discusses childbirth
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 May 12 (Box 2)
  the completion of the Episcopal church at the University where she heard Mr. Meade preach, a description of Virginia's new baby, the plan of Harriet, Lucy, and Jane Randolph to open a school for girls in New London and leave Ashton, the mention of Jefferson's arrangement to purchase a clock for the University when finances allowed
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1826 May 29 (Box 2)
  congratulates her on the arrival of her daughter, reports she has had no nurse for some time saying, "The curse of domestic life in New England is the insolence and insubordination of the servants and the difficulty of getting any that do not give more trouble than they save." She then describes her child care experiences, and says she has not heard from brother Jeff
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 June 6 (Box 2)
  mentions seeing an elephant at an exhibition of animals in Charlottesville, her visit to the Rotunda, hearing a speech from a member of the Patrick Henry Society at the University, and Thomas Jefferson's ride into Charlottesville
- Virginia Trist to Cornelia Randolph 1826 June 30 (Box 2)
  describes the state of Thomas Jefferson's declining health after his recent attack, the bedside vigils of the family, her regret that they are not all together [Ellen and Cornelia did not arrive before the funeral
- Nicholas P. Trist to Joseph Coolidge 1826 July 4 (Box 2)
  writes that Thomas Jefferson has lived to see the fourth of July, and describes the desperate condition of Jefferson at the point of death, his determination to follow the doctor's instructions without complaint, and the importance of their coming to Martha
- Joseph Coolidge to [?] 1826 July 5 (Box 2)
  writes that they will leave as soon as possible for Monticello refers to the death of President John Adams at Quincy on July fourth
- Ellen Coolidge to Jeff Randolph 1826 September 7 (Box 2)
  thanks him for the use of the carriage to begin their journey home, informs Jeff that they missed the Norfolk boat, and that Joseph was too unwell to travel further
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 September 11 (Box 2)
  expresses her regret at their absence, describes the beautiful surroundings at Monticello, and reveals Martha's fear that she will return home from a trip to Boston to find Monticello sold and gone forever
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1826 September 14 (Box 2)
  describes her stay in Richmond, refers to her home in Boston as "a state of exile," describes the rivalry of two steamboats plying from Richmond to Norfolk, and her fear of disease at Richmond
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph and Nicholas Trist 1826 September 27 (Box 2)
  requests that Martha and Nicholas supply information concerning the private life of Thomas Jefferson and the causes of his indebtedness in old age for an article, and lists causes known to her as 1) he lost much in the Revolutionary War 2) the depreciation of paper money 3) his father-in-law's debts assumed by Jefferson 4) lack of time during his Presidency to watch over his affairs at Monticello 5) the enormous establishment at Monticello far beyond his means of support
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 October 1 (Box 2)
  reports that the success of the lottery is extremely doubtful and that the lottery has been put off until December 5, but it seems impossible to sell even half of the tickets by then, should the lottery fail the Bedford property will be sold on January 1, 1827, including the furniture from Monticello and part of the slaves, if everything must be sold then Martha might open up a school upon her return from Boston, the rest of the family will go to Tufton until she returns, Jefferson's proposal of abandoning Monticello to accentuate the real state of the family's financial affairs, and the visit of Mrs. Madison during a meeting of the Board of Visitors at the University
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 October 30 (Box 2)
  writes concerning Martha's departure for Boston, her visit to Montpelier, the work in shutting up the house at Monticello to leave for Tufton, her sorrow and despair at the thought of leaving Monticello, and Mr. Madison's mother
- Cornielia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 November 12 (Box 2)
  sends a package of trees to Ellen and some to Mrs. Coolidge and other objects for the rest of the family, including clothes, books, pincusions and hams, and mentions Yellow Fever raging in Norfolk
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 November 26 (Box 2)
  writes concerning her homesickness for Monticello which they have just left for Tufton, plans for Lewis Randolph to attend Mr. Giles' school next session, the removal of Virginia's piano from Monticello, the destruction of Carysbrook by fire, and her experiences in teaching the household children
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1826 December 11 (Box 2)
  discusses all possible ways of making a living, her fear of being dependent on her brother Jefferson who believes them all extravagant, her work in copying her grandfather's letters, her admiration for Thomas Jefferson's perservering attitude under adversity in his public and private life, and speaks of the exodus of Virginians seeking a better life elsewhere
- "Essay on Thomas Jefferson by Ellen Coolidge 1826 (Box 2)
  concerning Thomas Jefferson's financial affairs and the causes of his indebtedness and financial ruin
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1827 January 7 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the health of her mother, and her desire of some relic of her grandfather's from the library or bedroom
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1827 January 25 (Box 2)
  refers to the financial help rendered to the family by the South Carolina legislature, the proposal of opening a school in Charlottesville to be taught and run by the girls, requests her mother's ideas on the subject, hopes to eventually recover Monticello in a few years, refers to the sale of Monticello and the slaves and the pain it brought to the family
- Cornelia Randolph and Nicholas Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1827 February 4 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the education of Ben and Lewis, her bitterness against the Virginia Legislature which offered no financial help for Thomas Jefferson, the inactivity about starting the proposed school, where they want to teach French, Italian, English, drawing, music, and for which she is busy collecting everybody's ideas
- Virginia Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1827 February 11 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the proposed division of labor in the school, the possibility of Nicholas setting up a law practice in Washington, and the desire of Jeff for his grandfather's octagon table
- [Mary Randolph] to Ellen Coolidge 1827 March 18 (Box 2)
  writes concerning her visit to the University, the completion of the portico of the Rotunda and its beauty, remarks on the quietness of the session at the University due in part to the new regulations which limit the amount of pocket money allowed to students and discourages visits to the confectioners and taverns, the family's dental work, the aid of the Louisiana Legislature to the family, her hopes that a school will yet be unnecessary, Louisiana as a land of opportunity, and mentions that Simon Bolivar's nephew, Fernando Bolivar, attends the University
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1827 March 20 (Box 2)
  reveals her intense trouble with her domestic servants and her frustrations in dealing with them, her mother's health improved, the receipt of a letter from her father in Georgia mentioning oranges in leaf and the delicious climate, arguments among Martha's children and Septimia's bad behavior, waiting for a clock by Simon Willard to be finished for the University, mentions the $ 10,000 contribution of the Louisiana Legislature, the octagon table, and the many personal treasures of Thomas Jefferson already possessed by Jeff
- Virginia Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1827 March 23 (Box 2)
  discusses the idea of moving the family to Louisiana to the Trist sugar plantation where they might make a good living, her fears of the climate there, mentions brother Jeff is in New York about the sale of the lottery tickets and her fears that they will not be a success, hopes her mother does not intend to use the money from the South Carolina and Louisiana Legislatures to pay the creditors of Thomas Jefferson instead of her own needs, shares their uncertainty over Nicholas' plans, her desire to be settled, depredations on the Monticello property perpetuated by visitors to the estate, quarrels over the octagon table, and the relinquishing of the plan to start a school
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1827 April 10 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the failure of the lottery scheme due partially to laws passed against it by New York and Maryland, Jeff's hopes of using the proceeds from the sale of Jefferson's papers to pay Jefferson's debts, and describes several members of the early University faculty
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1827 April 22 (Box 2)
  describes her visit and the routine at Bremo Recess, and the visit of Philip St. George Cocke on holiday from the University to Bremo Recess, which John Hartwell Cocke lent to Aunt Cary because Carybrook burnt to the ground
- Virginia Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1827 May 1 (Box 2)
  acknowledges the receipt of the box of gifts, writes concerning her irritation at the vulgar visitors who traveled to Monticello, the devotion of Burwell who remained at Monticello to take care of the yard and the house, and the interest of Jared Sparks in Thomas Jefferson's papers
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1827 May 18 (Box 2)
  describes a visit to Monticello to air out the house and bedding, Burwell's faithful keeping of the house and yard at Monticello, her mixture of pleasure and pain experienced during her visits to Monticello, the house Jeff intends to build at Edgehill and the property there
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1827 June 11 (Box 2)
  mentions the visit of Virginia and Nicholas to the Dunglisons, the upcoming marriage of Louisiana Cocke and Dr. Falcon, the ride to Edgehill with Jeff and Jane and describes Edgehill as being in disrepair and covered with vegetative growth
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1827 July 16 (Box 2)
  mentions her discomfort from her pregnancy, her enjoyment of living in Cambridge, news of George and Septimia, her father's refusal of a position as an Indian agent
- Joseph Coolidge to Virginia Trist [1827] July 23 (Box 2)
  urges that Martha should stay in Cambridge a while longer, and not return to live with Thomas Mann Randolph who was back in Albemarle County, citing her liking of Cambridge, the company of his aunt, and the new school for boys begun by Mr. Wells, a well-known classical scholar, author of Scriptores Romani, which George could attend, believes that if she remained with them it would discourage Thomas Mann Randolph from staying in Albemarle and force him to support himself, suggests that Benjamin accept the position as a junior engineer to gain experience in surveying and includes other advice for the family
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1827 July 29 (Box 2)
  writes of opening up Monticello for the Dunglisons to spend their vacation, their plan to return to Monticello for the fall in preparation for Martha's return from Boston, her fear that Aunt Cary will again suggest a uniting of the two misplaced families in one house, or indulge in several long visits to Monticello during the winter, suggests an arrangement to secure furniture for Monticello from the interest on the South Carolina appropriation and ways to economize and discourage guests, notes that the Keys have left for England, Sally Cole plans to work for Dr. Emmet when he returns from New York with his bride, and mentions the law forbidding her to remain in the state after she has secured her freedom
- Joseph Coolidge to Jefferson Randolph 1828 February 10 (Box 2)
  passes on an inquiry from the trustees of the Boston Athenaeum who hope to purchase any of Thomas Jefferson's collection of pamphlets at Monticello not included in the sale of books
- Thomas Mann Randolph to and from Nicholas Trist 1828 March 10-11 (Box 2)
  Randolph requests permission to occupy the North Pavilion at Monticello since Martha intends on returning to Monticello in May under the following conditions, "Mr. R. means to live entirely in his own room, at his own charge, making no part of the family, and receiving nothing from it in any way whatever. He will come on no other terms; & he assures Mr. T. that there shall be no other communication than the sight of him as he goes in and out. He wants only a place for his horse; the cellar under the house; one of the carriage houses for his fuel which he will procure himself; and a small spot for a garden, to be enclosed by him." Trist gives him permission to live there and invites him to do so as one of the family, but Randolph replys that his own peace of mind requires an absolute separation from the others at Monticello
- Virginia Trist to Ellen Coolidge 1828 March 19 (Box 2)
  gives an account of Thomas Mann Randolph's return to Monticello occupying the North Pavilion in solitude which no one disturbs except to inquire about his health, the family's determination not to let him disturb her mother's peace of mind, the need for Nicholas to seek employment elsewhere, the prospects in Louisiana and her opposition to moving there and leaving her mother, the rising fortune of the Nicholas family
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1828 May 2 (Box 2)
  describes her voyage from Boston to New York City, where she visited Morrisania [home of Gouverneur Morris]
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1828 May 6 (Box 2)
  sends news of acquaintances in Cambridge and the family who miss her greatly, and the wedding of [Sarah ?] Bradford
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1828 May 13 (Box 2)
  mentions her sorrow on the absence of her mother, her fears for her peace of mind, the safe arrival of the Jefferson paintings formerly at Monticello, and her dreams involving Monticello
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1828 May 24 (Box 2)
  describes several gentlemen they met on the voyage home from Philadelphia to Baltimore, including a Congressman [Richard Henry] Wilde (1789-1847) from Georgia, her distaste for the fiction of Mrs. Royal, especially The Black Book, the ruin and desolation of Richmond, their arrival home and the good health of Martha, speaks of "one of those industrious plebians of Fluvanna," a Mr. Magruder of the Union Mills in Fluvanna and his difficulty in getting women to work in his mill "as hirelings and particularly in so public a manner." and mentions the sickness of Thomas Mann Randolph
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1828 May 28 (Box 2)
  describes the celebration of the election day in Boston, her visit to the Athenaeum in Boston where she saw many of the paintings from Monticello, some of which she lists by name and gives their estimated value, mentions Joseph's intention of getting [Washington?] Allston the painter to make a fourth evaluation of their worth, and reveals her low estimation of the quality of Boston domestics
- Autobiographical Writings of Ellen Coolidge 1828 June 15-July 13 (Box 2)